Guide to the Advertising Council Records, 1935-1999 and undated RL.00013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Advertising Council records
1935-1999 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Advertising Council
RL.00013
19 Linear Feet
12,150 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Advertising Council Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from the University of Illinois at Urbanna-Champaign and the Campbell-Ewald advertising agency in 1998-1999.
Historical Note
Advertising campaigns that supported the war effort were designed by the War Advertising Council and approved by appropriate U.S. government agencies during World War II. Actual advertisements were in turn sponsored by various businesses that would often add their company name to the ads. After the end of World War II, The War Advertising Council continued to produce public service campaigns. The name changed to the Advertising Council, more popularly known as the Ad Council.
Collection Overview
The Advertising Council Records span the years from 1935 to 1999, and primarily consist of public service advertising campaigns developed by the Advertising Council. The campaigns are documented through council booklets, brochures, published articles, and sample advertisements which were distributed to Ad Council members and participating advertising agencies. Particular ad campaigns that are well represented include U.S. Savings Bonds and United Service Organizations (USO) during World War II; Religion in American Life; the Red Cross; the creation of Smokey the Bear and related fire prevention campaigns circa 1941 to 1951; and a campaign to explain the American Economic System, circa 1950 to 1957 (Cold War anti-communism). Various campaigns throughout the 1960s and 1970s are also represented to a lesser extent, including the War on Poverty, Equal Opportunity, and Child Abuse.
The collection is organized into two main series: General Files and Campaigns. The General Files Series contains Ad Council materials that are not specific to particular campaigns, such as annual reports, correspondence, and Ad Council promotional materials. The Campaigns Series, which comprises about two-thirds of the collection, contains pamphlets, brochures, posters, newspaper articles, and memos concerning the strategies of over 100 public service advertising campaigns. Large-format materials from both of these series have been relocated to the Oversize Materials.
Related collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library include the J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives: Domestic Advertisements Collection, the War Effort Mobilization Campaigns Poster Collection, the Edgar Hatcher Papers, the Warwick Baker O'Neill Records, and the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA) Archives. The official archives of the Ad Council resides at the University of Illinois--Urbana/Champaign.
Memoranda; World War, 1939-1945 -- Finance -- United States; United Service Organizations (U.S.); War Advertising Council; Pamphlets; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Public Opinion; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Mass media and the war; Advertising -- History -- 20th century; Propaganda, American -- History -- 20th century; Clippings (information artifacts); Public relations; Advertising -- Political aspects -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Family Violence -- United States -- Prevention; Advertising forest fire prevention -- United States; Advertising Council -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- United States; Smokey Bear; Savings bonds -- United States -- History; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1989 -- Public opinion; Cold War -- Social aspects -- United States; Child abuse -- United States; Religion in American Life, Inc.; Red Cross and Red Crescent; Posters; Advertising Council; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- General Files Series, 1935-1999 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Advertising Council administrative and published materials that are not specific to particular campaigns, such as annual reports, brochures, correspondence, meeting minutes, press releases, and reports. This series is divided into the following subseries: Administrative Files, Publications, and Promotional Materials. Arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  - Administrative Files Subseries, 1945-1990 and undated
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1945-1965, 7 folders (Box 1A)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1965-1987, 7 folders (Box 1B)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1967-1979, 7 folders (Box 1C)
    - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980-1988, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Campaign Review Committee Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1979 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-1970 (Box 2)
      [Additional materials may be found in Oversize Box 43]
    - Special Events, 1947-1977; 1990-1995; and undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Unpublished Reports, 1945-1990 and undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Publications Subseries, 1943-1993 and undated
    - Ad Council, Items About, undated (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1945-1967, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1969-1990, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Economic Communicator, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
    - Press Clippings, 1946-1993 (Box 5)
    - Published Reports and Informational Brochures - General, 1947-1971, Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 5)
    - Published Reports and Informational Brochures - General, 1947-1971, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 6)
    - Published Reports and Informational Brochures - WWII, 1943-1945 (Box 6)
  - Promotional Materials Subseries, 1946-1999
    - House Magazine Copy, 1956-1968 (Box 6)
    - Public Service Advertising Bulletin, 1969-1999, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Innercom, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Innercom, 1970 (Box 7)
    - Magazine Service Bulletin, 1960-1971, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Allocations, 1967-1986, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1993 (Box 8)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Business Press, 1966 July - 1975 May, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Business Press, 1975 May - 1980 Sept., 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Business Press, 1980 Oct. - 1993 Nov., 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Company Publications, 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Consumer Magazines, 1971 Nov.-1974 Feb. (Box 11)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Consumer Magazines, 1974 June-1979 Dec., 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Consumer Magazines, 1980 Jan.-1982 Dec., 5 folders (Box 13)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Consumer Magazines, 1983-1988 and undated, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Public Service Advertisements for Editors, 1976-1978 (Box 14)
- Campaigns Series, 1939-1998 and undated
  Contains sample advertisements, pamphlets, brochures, posters, newspaper articles, radio spots and memos concerning the strategies of over 100 public service advertising campaigns. Arranged alphabetically by the title of each campaign.
  - Action, 1971-1977 (Box 15)
  - Ad Council, 1967-1981 and undated (Box 15)
  - Agricultural Census, 1987-1988 (Box 15)
  - Aid to Higher Education, 1966-1985 and undated, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Alcoholism: A Treatable Disease, 1982-1984 (Box 16)
  - Alliance to Save Energy, 1974-1984 (Box 16)
  - American Cancer Society, 1988 (Box 16)
  - American Economic System, 1948-1981 and undated, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - American Economic System, assorted pamphlets, undated (Box 16)
  - American Heritage, 1947-1952 (Box 16)
  - American Legion, 1949 (Box 16)
  - Anti-Inflation, 1959, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
  - Armed Forces Blood Donor Program, 1951 (Box 17)
  - Be a Voter, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Better Community Relations, 1966 (Box 17)
  - Better Schools, 1953-1958 (Box 17)
  - Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1987 (Box 17)
  - Boy Scouts of America, 1954 (Box 17)
  - Cambodian Crisis, 1980 (Box 17)
  - CARE, undated (Box 17)
  - Carpooling, 1974-1978 and undated, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - Census, 1970, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Census, 1980, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Challenge to Americans, 1963-1964 (Box 18)
  - Child Abuse, 1976-1994, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Child Find Mediation, 1987 (Box 19)
  - Citizens for a New Prosperity, 1971 (Box 19)
  - Clean Water, undated (Box 19)
  - Clothing Collection for Overseas Relief, 1945 (Box 19)
  - Confidence in a Growing America, 1958-1961 (Box 19)
  - Consumer Information, 1972-1975 (Box 19)
  - Continue Your Education, 1966-1970, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Co-op Education, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
  - Crime Prevention, 1979-1981 (Box 19)
  - Crime Prevention, 1982-1998, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Crisis in Our Cities, 1968 (Box 20)
  - Direct Deposit, 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Disabled Persons, 1982 (Box 20)
  - Domestic Violence, undated (Box 20)
  - Driver Energy Awareness, 1980 (Box 20)
  - Drug Abuse Information, 1969-1971 (Box 20)
  - Drug Abuse Information, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Drug Abuse Prevention, 1984-1986, 1992, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Drunk Driving, 1970, 1992 and undated (Box 21)
  - Economic Census, 1987 (Box 21)
  - Economic Stabilization, 1943-1945 (Box 21)
  - Education Reform, 1993 (Box 21)
  - Emergency Food Collection on Behalf of the UNRRA, 1946 (Box 21)
    [United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration]
  - Employer Support of the Guard and Reserve, 1973-1993 and undated, 6 folders (Box 22)
  - Energy Conservation, 1974 and undated (Box 23)
  - Engineers Wanted, undated (Box 23)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity, 1967 and undated, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Export Awareness, 1987 (Box 23)
  - Export Development, 1977-1979 (Box 23)
  - Fair Campaign Practices, 1976 (Box 23)
  - Famine Emergency, 1946 (Box 23)
  - Food Fights For Freedom, 1941-1944 (Box 23)
  - Food Nutrition and Health, 1970-1978 (Box 23)
  - Forest Fire Prevention, 1945-1978, 6 folders (Box 24)
    [Additional materials may be found in Oversize Box 44]
  - Forest Fire Prevention, 1979-1988, 7 folders (Box 25)
  - Forest Fire Prevention, 1992-1993 and undated, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Free Press, 1987 (Box 26)
  - Freedom from Hunger, 1963 (Box 26)
  - Freedoms Foundations Awards, 1950 (Box 26)
  - Future of America, 1955 (Box 26)
  - Get Out the Vote, 1996, 1998 (Box 26)
  - Health Careers, 1974-1975 (Box 26)
  - Health Careers, 1976-1977 (Box 27)
  - Help Prevent Crime, 1969 (Box 27)
  - Help Prevent Homefires, 1952 (Box 27)
  - Help Young America Work, 1980-1981 (Box 27)
  - High Blood Pressure Education, 1975-1983 and undated (Box 27)
  - Hoover Report, 1948 (Box 27)
  - Hope, 1960 (Box 27)
  - Hospital Career, 1945-1948 (Box 27)
  - Individual Giving/Volunteering, 1987 (Box 27)
  - Infant Immunization, undated (Box 27)
  - Inflation Can Be Stopped, 1980 (Box 27)
  - Interfaith Hunger Appeal, 1981-1983 (Box 27)
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1988 (Box 27)
  - International Executives Service Corps, 1984-1986 (Box 27)
  - International Youth Exchange, 1983-1984 (Box 28)
  - Invite and Welcome Foreign Visitors, 1969-1970 (Box 28)
  - Jobs (National Alliance of Businessmen), 1968-1974, 1979 and undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Jobs for Veterans, 1971-1978 and undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Keep America Beautiful, 1961-1965 (Box 28)
  - Keep America Beautiful, 1966-1975 and undated, 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Know Mexico, 1964 (Box 29)
  - Mental Retardation, 1968 (Box 29)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, 1971-1975 (Box 29)
  - Multiple Campaigns (Assorted), 1968-1973, 1981-1986, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Multiple Campaigns (Assorted), 1987-1993, 3 folders (Box 30)
  - National Council on the Aging, 1976 (Box 30)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1978-1979 (Box 30)
  - National Institute on Drug Abuse, 1983 (Box 30)
  - National Urban Coalition, 1970 (Box 30)
  - Neighborhood Housing Services, 1984 (Box 30)
  - Opportunities for Minorities, 1982-1986 (Box 30)
  - Pakistan Relief Fund, 1971 (Box 30)
  - Paper Conservation, 1944-1945 (Box 30)
  - Peace Corps, 1963-1970, 1980-1988, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - People's Capitalism, 1956-1959 (Box 31)
  - Population, 1971-1973 (Box 31)
  - Prejudice, ca. 1960s (Box 31)
  - Prisoners of War, 1971-1972 (Box 31)
  - Productivity Project, 1972-1973 (Box 31)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1951-1970 (Box 32)
  - Radon, 1991 (Box 32)
  - Recycling, 1980 (Box 32)
  - Red Cross, 1947, 1968-1981, 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Red Cross, 1982-1987, 5 folders (Box 33)
  - Red Cross, 1988 and undated (Box 34)
  - Register and Vote, 1956, 1966, 1976 (Box 34)
  - Rehabilitation of Handicapped People, 1968-1975 and undated, 3 folders (Box 34)
  - Religion in American Life, 1966-1969, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Religion in American Life, 1969-1975, 6 folders (Box 35)
  - Religion in American Life, 1977-1986 and undated (Box 36)
  - Residential Energy, 1980-1981 (Box 36)
  - Safety Belt Education, 1987 (Box 36)
  - Save the Survivors (Pakistan Relief Fund), 1971 (Box 36)
  - Scrap Metal Drive, 1942-1947 (Box 36)
  - Security of War Information, 1943 (Box 36)
  - Small Business Foundation, 1950 (Box 36)
  - Small Claims Court, 1973 (Box 36)
  - Smoking, 1969 (Box 36)
  - Southern Forest Fire Prevention, 1964-1971, 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Southern Forest Fire Prevention, 1972-1978, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Statue of Liberty/Ellis Island Centennial, 1983-1986 (Box 37)
  - Stop Accidents, 1946-1952 (Box 37)
  - Student Nurse Recruitment, 1954 (Box 37)
  - Summer Jobs for Youth, 1967-1984 (Box 37)
  - Support the Arts (National Endowment for the Arts), 1978 (Box 37)
  - Take Pride in America, 1987 (Box 37)
  - Technical Education and Training, 1969-1980 and undated, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - Traffic Safety, 1948-1978 and undated, 2 folders (Box 38)
  - Understanding Mental Illness, 1986-1987, 1993, 2 folders (Box 38)
  - United Nations Association (UNA-USA), 1952-1968, 1972-1976 and undated, 2 folders (Box 39)
  - United Negro College Fund, 1972-1987 and undated, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - United Service Organizations (USO), 1941-1971 and undated, 3 folders (Box 40)
  - United States Army V-Mail, 1944 (Box 40)
  - United States Savings Bonds, 1942-1957, 1966-1983, 3 folders (Box 40)
    [Additional materials may be found in Oversize Folder 1]
  - United States Savings Bonds, 1983-1984 and undated (Box 41)
  - United Way, 1970-1984, 2 folders (Box 41)
  - Venereal Disease Awareness, 1944-1975 (Box 41)
  - Victory Gardens, 1946 (Box 41)
  - Vista, 1978 (Box 41)
  - Volunteer, 1973-1975 (Box 41)
  - Volunteer Aganist Illiteracy, 1986 (Box 41)
  - Vote '84, 1984 (Box 42)
  - Vote '86, 1986 (Box 42)
  - War to Peace Transition, 1945-1947 (Box 42)
  - World Hunger, 1946-1947 (Box 42)
  - Youth Alcoholism Prevention, 1986 (Box 42)
  - Zip Code, 1967-1970 and undated, 2 folders (Box 42)
  - 55 MPH Speed Limit, 1976-1978 (Box 42)
- Oversize Materials, 1935-1987 and undated
  - General Files Series, 1935-1952 and undated
    - Miscellaneous Reports, 1935-1952 and undated (Oversize-box 43)
    - Norman Rockwell Prints, ca. 1943 (Oversize-box 43)
      [Undated prints of The Four Freedoms, which were published in the Saturday Evening Post in 1943]
  - Campaigns Series, 1939-1987 and undated
    - Advertising (Truth About...), 1939-1962 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Advertising Council, 1946-1971 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Alliance to Save Energy, 1979 (Oversize-box 43)
    - American Economic System, 1940s-1970s (Oversize-box 43)
    - American Heritage Crusade for Freedom, undated (Oversize-box 43)
    - Army Prestige Campaign, ca. 1947 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Care Food Campaign, ca. 1955 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Challenge to Americans, undated (Oversize-box 43)
    - Crisis in Our Cities, 1968 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Crime Prevention, 1985 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Drug Abuse, 1970 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Education, ca. 1970 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Emergency Food Collection for UNRRA, 1946 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Employer Support for the Guard and Reserve, 1973 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Energy Conservation, 1974 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity, 1967 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Famine Emergency Relief, World Hygiene, 1946 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Fight Inflation, 1959 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Fight Waste, 1944 (Oversize-box 43)
    - Forest Fire Prevention, 1949-1965, 2 folders (Oversize-box 44)
    - Free Press, 1987 (Oversize-box 44)
    - General Safety, 1948 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Higher Education, 1967-1972 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Hospital Career Campaign, 1947-1948 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Inflation, 1951 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Keep America Beautiful, 1967 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Mental Retardation, 1968 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Miscellaneous (Edward Petry and Company), undated (Oversize-box 44)
    - National Goals (Eisenhower), 1960 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Nursing, 1946 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Our Teachers Mold Our Nation's Future, 1947-1948 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Peace Corps, 1967-1968 (Oversize-box 44)
    - People's Capitalism, 1956 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Productivity Project, 1973 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Radio Free Europe, 1951 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Register and Vote, 1956 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Religion in American Life, 1956-1957 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Savings Bank, 1945-1974 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Scrap Paper Drive, 1944 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Summer Youth, 1967 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Traffic Safety, 1948-1958 (Oversize-box 44)
    - United America, 1948-1949 (Oversize-box 44)
    - United Negro College Fund, 1978 (Oversize-box 44)
    - United Service Organizations (USO), 1967 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Venereal Disease, 1975 (Oversize-box 44)
    - War Bonds, 1943-1944 (Oversize-box 44)
    - World Trade, ca. 1948 (Oversize-box 44)
    - Youth Alcoholism Prevention, 1986 (Oversize-box 44)
    - United States Savings Bonds, 1945-1950 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Accession (2005-0079), 1963-1997, 4 boxes
  Addition (2005-0079) (474 items; 2.3 lin. ft.; dated 1963-1997) comprises press and radio kits; advertising proofs; reports; booklets, photographs of Advertising Council events; issues of Public Service Advertising Bulletin; and clippings.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Closed to researchers pending processing.
- Accession (2009-0159), 2004-2007, 1 box
  Addition (2009-0159) (20 items; 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 2004-2007) includes annual reports, Public Service Advertising Bulletins, PSA dinner programs, and nutrition education press releases.
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 1)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - PSA Bulletins
    - 2005 November/December (Box 1)
    - 2006 January/February (Box 1)
    - 2006 May/June (Box 1)
    - 2006 July/August (Box 1)
    - 2006 November/December (Box 1)
    - 2007 March/April (Box 1)
    - 2007 May/June (Box 1)
    - 2007 September/October (Box 1)
    - 2007 November/December (Box 1)
  - PSA Dinner programs, 2004 and 2007 (Box 1)
  - Nutrition Education press releases, undated (Box 1)